<!--
  Copyright (c) 2006 Benedikt Meurer <benny@xfce.org>
-->

<refentry id="Thunar">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Thunar</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Thunar</refname>
    <refpurpose>File Manager for the Xfce Desktop Environment</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>Thunar</command>
      <arg choice="opt">options</arg>
      <arg rep="repeat">
        <arg>URI</arg>
      </arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>Thunar</command>
      <arg choice="opt">options</arg>
      <arg choice="plain">--bulk-rename</arg>
      <arg rep="repeat">
        <arg>URI</arg>
      </arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>Thunar</command>
      <arg choice="opt">options</arg>
      <arg choice="plain">--quit</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      <command>Thunar</command> is a fast and easy to use file manager for the Xfce Desktop Environment. It
      has been designed from the ground up to be lighweight with special focus on usability. Its user
      interface is clean and intuitive, and does not include any confusing or useless options.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Invocation</title>
    <para>
      <command>Thunar</command> takes a list of <replaceable>URI</replaceable>s for folders that should be
      opened in new file manager windows or files that should be run using the default application for their
      types. The <replaceable>URI</replaceable>s may be specified as either <emphasis role="bold">file:</emphasis>
      or <emphasis role="bold">trash:</emphasis> URIs, absolute paths or paths relative to the current directory
      from which <command>Thunar</command> is being invoked. If no <replaceable>URI</replaceable>s are specified,
      the current folder will be opened in a new file manager window.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the <option>--bulk-rename</option> option is specified no file managers windows will be opened, but instead
      the <replaceable>URI</replaceable>s will be passed to the bulk renamer. The bulk renamer allows to
      rename several files or folders at once using different renamer modules.
    </para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Options</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>-?</option>, <option>--help</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Print brief help and exit.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>-v</option>, <option>--version</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Print version information and exit.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>-B</option>, <option>--bulk-rename</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Open the <replaceable>URI</replaceable>s in a standalone window of the bulk renamer.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--daemon</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Do not terminate the <command>Thunar</command> instance when the last window is closed, but keep
              it running to speed up opening new windows later on. This is the default when spawning <command>Thunar</command>
              as part of the default Xfce session or when using D-Bus activation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>--display=DISPLAY</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the specified X <option>DISPLAY</option> for the user interface.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><option>-q</option>, <option>--quit</option></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Terminate any <command>Thunar</command> instance running in the background (spawned using the
              <option>--daemon</option> option). This command should be used whenever <command>Thunar</command>
              is upgraded to a new version to ensure that no old instance is reused.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Author</title>
    <para>
      <command>Thunar</command> was written by Benedikt Meurer <email>benny@xfce.org</email>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This manual page was written by Benedikt Meurer <email>benny@xfce.org</email>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
